Chernoff Hoeffding bound, we saw that already.
So that is one result right we looked at it
in the last class and you saw how we used
it to manage to bound the regret of UCB right
so we will be looking at yet another class
of bandit algorithms today right so the PAC
bandits and we will be using the Chernoff
hoeffding bound again to bound a slightly
different quantity but nevertheless of interest
you remember the Markov inequality Elec people,
people who did probability theory one form
of writing it is this which is what we will
need
right assuming a is, a is positive, the expected.
So, the x support is in the positive range
I mean so I mean whatever makes appropriate
sense for you to make sure that this is a
probability right next thing you use is the
Union bound
this is this all of you should know the probability
of the union of multiple events right is less
than or equal to the sum of the probabilities
of the individual events that is rather straightforward
it has a fancy name called Union bound right
so whenever somebody says oh, hence by Union
bound we can write this result essentially
all they are saying is that they are upper
bounding the probability of the joint event
by the sum of the probabilities of the individual
events okay these are the results we will
just keep using them as we will do some of
the proofs today.
Okay so we talked about multiple solution
concepts for bandit algorithms right so the
first one was asymptotic correctness and the
second one we talked about was regret optimality
which we already looked at one example of
a regret optimal algorithm UCB or UCB1 more
correctly even though popularly when people
say UCB they refer to UCB1 right and then
what is the third one pac optimality right
which was the probably approximately correct
thing where you are trying to bound with some
probability right that I mean you are close
enough to the true solution right So that
is essentially the guarantee that we want
to give right.
So what we look at today are
right so pac bounds for multi-armed bandit
problems right I will start off with a very,
very simple algorithm start off with a very,
very simple algorithm right this is just to
get you started right it is not a true algorithm
that you have to use, its just to get you
started so I have an input which is I will
give you an epsilon and a delta and what I
am asking for is a guarantee that at the end
of this algorithm the arm that I return to
you will be epsilon close to the optimal arm
with probability 1 minus delta.
Right with a very high probability if when
this algorithm finishes running with a very
high probability I will give you an arm which
is epsilon close to the true arm the payoff
of the arm that I give you will be epsilon
close to the true arm so if you remember the
pac guarantee that we wrote right so most
pac algorithm pac style algorithms essentially
take this epsilon and delta as inputs right
and they determine some parameters of the
algorithms based on this epsilon and delta
okay so I am writing the algorithm in the
same style as it is in the paper that we will
give you to read so that it is easy for you
to map it.
Unfortunately I will still do the online translation
of notation so that you can compare across
multiple algorithms okay, and this paper is
way, way better written than the UCB paper
okay so it is actually you can understand
the paper when you read it okay so this is
the on the median elimination algorithm by
Eyal Even-Dar, Shie Mannor and Yishay Mansour
okay, it is titled Action elimination for
Reinforcement Learning okay so the nice thing
about this ok I will tell you the nice things
about the paper later.
But the really nice thing about the paper
is it is well written so you can easily read
it. very simple algorithm right the algorithm
is a very simple algorithm what is the n in
the log, where where, what is n inside the
log, n is the number of arms right so what
did I say I changed it to K right sorry yeah
you are right over in the last class, last
lecture I changed it to K yeah right this
is a very simple algorithm all I am saying
is take each arm sample it some number of
times okay we can think about it right this
is this will work see if I if I get a good
enough estimate for each arm right if you
get a good enough estimate of the reward of
each arm then I can say that with a very high
probability I will be epsilon optimal right.
So this of course there is always a small
chance that I will go wrong right do you see
what I am saying here so the idea is very
simple so I will take an arm keep pulling
it many many times right until I have gotten
a good estimate of the of the expectation
right so remember the probability with which
it is going to come up with 1 or whatever
right so whatever is my expectation parameter
I will just keep pulling the arm multiple
times until I get a good estimate of the expectation
I will do that for each of the arms that I
have right.
And once I have a good enough estimate of
the expectation all I have to do is now go
and play the arm that has the highest expectation
right that is essentially what I am doing
here now the magic here is in that number
which I have written down there right I mean
given K, epsilon and delta that is actually
a number okay remember I take epsilon and
everything as inputs given all of this is
actually a it is actually a number right so
that magic number how did I produce somewhere
yeah I wrote all of this I wrote all of these
things so that you know that you are going
to use them to produce that magic number so
it is very simple.
So let us make things a little formal so we
call this algorithm naive, so then algorithm
Naive which takes as input epsilon delta is
an epsilon delta pac algorithm, you remember
what is epsilon delta pac we defined it in
the earlier lecture right epsilon delta pac
gives you that whatever guarantees you are
talking about right epsilon delta pac algorithm
with arm sample complexity essentially the
number of times you pull the arms given by
order of n by epsilon squared into log n by
delta right so this part is obvious right
I pull each arm 1 by epsilon square times
ln K by delta right so for n arms I have to
do that n times so my overall sample complexity
is this okay, so the interesting part now
is to show that it is actually epsilon delta
pac whats it obviously yeah for today's lecture
if I write n by mistake right please point
it out to me.
So I will correct it to K right okay so how
do we prove it well the sample complexity
part is obvious we do not have to prove that
we just have to prove the epsilon delta pac
so for that we will assume that let a prime
be an arm such that
q star a prime okay so a prime is an arm which
is not epsilon optimal right an arm that is
epsilon optimal is epsilon close to the best
arm right so q star a star is the reward corresponding
to the best arm we know that right so I am
saying that I will pick an arm a prime such
that it is at least epsilon away from q star
a star right.
So the q star of a prime is at least epsilon
away from q star a star right so that means
it is a bad arm right so arms that are more
than epsilon close to the true arm I do not
care right if I select them I am happy because
my guarantee is satisfied I really have to
worry about making a mistake which in this
case is selecting an arm that is more than
epsilon away from the true optimal okay so
basically we are looking at the event
right so this is what we want we are looking
at right so if this is the case then the algorithm
will output a prime instead of a star correct.
People onboard with me on this right so if
Q a prime is greater than Q a star, then my
algorithm will output at least it will not
output a star for me to select a prime as
the best arm at least this condition has to
be satisfied okay let us put it that way right
for my algorithm to output a prime as the
best arm for sure this condition must be satisfied
in fact a prime has to be higher than every
other arm right only then I will output that
but at least this condition has to be satisfied
so essentially I am going to look at the probability
of this happening all right and then we will
try to bound that right.
So people can see why we need this condition
right so if a prime has to be reported as
the best arm it has to be at least better
than a star right great so that is the condition
so already we are being little loose here
okay, this is not really the probability that
yes a prime will be the best arm okay but
it is only looking at some sub event of that
it is not all the events together but this
will give me at least a bound on the probability
so that is essentially why you are looking
at this event okay.
Right so what is happening here, let us say
that is my
that is my q star a star okay that is my right
and this gap is at least this gap is at least
epsilon, okay so there is this is the setup
that we have now so and I am making some estimate
of q star a prime which is Q a prime right
and I am making some estimate of q star a
star which is Q a star so the condition I
am asking is that Q prime a prime should be
higher than I mean Q a prime should be higher
than Q a star right.
So essentially I am saying that I should have
Q a prime here Q a star somewhere lower right
so this is the case I am looking at right
so this all automatically means that either
Q a prime has to be more than epsilon by two
from q star a prime right it should be at
least epsilon by more than epsilon by two
above or Q a star should be more than epsilon
by two below q star a star, right if they
are exactly epsilon by two they will be equal
I mean they won't be one above the other nights
if one is epsilon by two below other is epsilon
by two above so you can think of cases where
this is actually here right so this could
be here in which case q star I mean q star
a star has to be even below right it will
be more than epsilon away forget about epsilon
by two right so likewise for cases where you
are overestimating Q a star
Then this will also have to be higher than
that in which case again it will be more than
epsilon away right so the interesting case
is when it is in between the two right then
it has to at least one of them has to be epsilon
by two away from the true estimate right either
as a overestimate or as an underestimate right
is it clear so why I wrote this down, right
one of these two events has to be satisfied.
right I am just taking them as independent
events and summing them up and that still
be an upper bound on the total probability
you have right, making things simpler and
simpler for me and now what happens here it
kind of in the Chernoff space right.
So I can apply Chernoff bound here so what
would be the case here e power minus two epsilon
squared by four into l, yeah so let us do
that so this will be less than or equal to
e power minus two epsilon squared by four
into l, what about the other term, the same
right it is a symmetrical bound so if that
is plus epsilon by two or minus epsilon by
two, it is going to be the same right so is
it clear okay so now plug in this l there
so what do you get, hmm, so essentially what
we need to do now is adjust this l so that
all those things get cancelled out that is
basically what we are looking for right and
you will be left with what should you be left
with.
What should you be left with what do you think
you should be left with no no no I want this
probability delta this is the probability
of me making a mistake right so it should
be delta, should I be left with delta, not
quite this is the probability of me choosing
one non optimal arm by mistake what if all
my arms are non-optimal except the one optimal
arm right everything is away from that is
the worst case so I should have delta by K
or K-1 so we will take delta by K, okay that
is easier than and so this whole thing should
simplify to delta by K right so that is what
I should be looking for so what should be
my l right.
So this if we plug this in what will I get
so the four by epsilon squared will go so
I will get 2 ln 2K by delta, that is not quite
right
and what do I get then, yeah 2 into 2K by
delta so I will get delta by K I will get
delta by K right is it fine I simplify this
I get delta by K so now you know how you actually
come up with this magic number l right, by
actually deriving this bound and then figuring
out what else should I plug in here so that
I get the necessary error for the probability
okay
so that is just for one a prime hmm there
is a two outside right, two epsilon okay.
So this is clear this is a naive algorithm
and the analysis also is pretty simple, pretty
straightforward right so all of you are happy
with this right so if you if I give you an
algorithm with a slightly different way of
selecting actions you can all derive the complex
the l that is required basically great it
turns out that so we have produced this complexity
here right it turns out that it is almost
impossible to get rid of this 1 by epsilon
squared right and log 1 by delta right, so
when I try to come up with another pac algorithm
right I want to you remember what I said about
pac analysis.
So I will give you an epsilon delta and now
the interesting part is telling me how you
can achieve this epsilon delta with as few
samples as possible correct so in this case
I am telling you that this is the sample complexity
right and K figures in two places you have
a K by epsilon squared and log K by delta
right it turns out that this 1 by epsilon
squared and log of 1 by delta is very hard
to get rid of right but then people have come
up with and can you get rid of this K, it
should depend on K why at least once right.
I have to try every am at least one so I cannot
get rid of the K also right so the only thing
I can try and minimize here is well I can
try and get rid of this K right so I can try
to get rid of the log K dependency right and
then have K by epsilon squared log 1 by delta
roughly I can try to move in that direction
and once I reach there I will probably be
in, left with trying to get rid of this two
here right and try to make the 2 into 3 by
2 or 1.77 or something like that. you know
how these things proceed right so you can
try to optimize the constants but more or
less this 1 by epsilon squared and log 1 by
delta is something that will have to live
with okay.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights reserved